<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last terrible tempestious windes and weather Truely relating many lamentable ship-wracks, with drowning of many people, on the coasts of England, Scotland, France and Ireland: with the Iles of Wight, Garsey &amp; Iarsey. Shewing also, many great mis-fortunes, that haue lately hapned on land, by reason of the windes and rayne, in diuers places of this kingdome.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25840</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855309</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15572)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 863:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last terrible tempestious windes and weather Truely relating many lamentable ship-wracks, with drowning of many people, on the coasts of England, Scotland, France and Ireland: with the Iles of Wight, Garsey &amp; Iarsey. Shewing also, many great mis-fortunes, that haue lately hapned on land, by reason of the windes and rayne, in diuers places of this kingdome.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Edward Allde and John Beale] for Ios: Hunt and are to be sold by Iohn Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC. "Beale pr[inted]. only quire B".</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The great tempest.</note>
                  <note>"These things heereafter following were related to me by certaine saylers and countrey people, since the first were printed ..", D1-2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Storms --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Storms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The laſt terrible Tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous windes and weather.</p>
            <p>Truely Relating many Lamentable Ship-wracks, with drowning of many people, on the Coaſts of England, Scotland, France and Ireland: with the Iles of Wight, Garſey &amp; Iarſey.</p>
            <p>Shewing alſo, many great miſ-fortunes, that haue lately hapned on Land, by reaſon of the windes and rayne, in diuers places of this Kingdome.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Ioſ: Hunt</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>REader, I do here preſent vnto thee, &amp; to thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding (if thou haſt any) ſome part of the lamentable loſſes, &amp; vnrecouerable miſchances that haue happened by occaſion of theſe late bluſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſtormes of winde, and an innumerable deale of rayne, the which a great many thouſands haue too true cauſe to beleeue, becauſe they are ſharers in the miſfortunes that this outragious weather hath cauſed. Now if thou haſt ſuſtained no loſſe thy ſelfe, perhaps thou wilt not beleeue theſe things to be true that I haue written: but if thou wilt or doeſt beleeue, then pray to God that it will pleaſe him to giue them patience that are looſers, and humilitie that are winners, and giue God thankes that he hath ſo bleſt thee that thou haſt no ſhare in theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps. But if thou wilt not beleeue, goe and looke, or elſe remaine ſtill in thy vnbeleife.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:3"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE RELATION of the great loſſes both by Sea and Land, by reaſon of the late <hi>great Tempeſts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch and ſo great is the inna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hereditary peruerſenes of miſerable mankinds na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inclination, that though we infallibly know that God is infinite, and his waies paſt finding out: yea though wee generally confeſſe him to bee the Mighty, Eternall, euerlaſting, inſcrutable, incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible Iehouah, in whoſe hands are all things paſt, preſent and future. Though (I ſay) we confeſſe and profeſſe an externall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe that God can and will puniſh obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and ſtiffe-necked ſinners in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20796:4"/> of his confounding Iuſtice; yet we preſuming (becauſe it is ſaid his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is ouer all his workes) ſo much vpon his mercie, that we are altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull of his Iuſtice; So that for all notwithſtanding our knowledge, our confeſſion and profeſſion, wee liue in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, Epicuriſme, and in ſo many ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſorts of hydra-headed ſciſme, that if it be rightly vnderſtood, wee ſpend our times in this vnconſcionable world little better then in bruite Barbariſme: for I am verily perſwaded that God had neuer fewer trew ſeruants, nor more profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors then are in theſe daies, and ſurely it is to bee feared when God hath leaſt, the Diuel hath moſt. And wee are ſo lulled and rockt aſleepe in the ſecureles cradle of ſenſual ſecurity, by the (Prince of this World) the Diuell and his two neere kinſmen the worlde and the fleſh, that we (as it were) in ſpight of the Eternall God, tread and trample his ſacred lawes
<pb facs="tcp:20796:4"/> and ſanctified Teſtimonies vnder our prophane, vnhallowed, &amp; rebellious feet, and with a high hand, and an aſpiring hart, with millions of varieties of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, we ſeem to batter the glorious frame of Heauen, with thundering ſhot of our abhominable hell hatchd impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Theſe outragious Enormities dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouoking our moſt iuſt God to powre forth the conſuming vials of his incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed heauie Indignation, vpon all the miſgouerned ſonnes of ſinfull men. For as God is infinite in his mercie, ſo is hee infinite in his Iuſtice; and as our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions are numberles, ſo are the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rods and puniſhments vncountable that God vſes to inflict vpon vs, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by weake meanes to accompliſh great things, and confound the mighty; and ſometimes by elementall cauſes, as fire, aire, water, and earth, hee ſhewes his vniuerſall power in his iuſt confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding offenders; and ſometimes by vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded
<pb facs="tcp:20796:5"/> infections of plagues and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencious feuers, and many thouſand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable maladies. And I thinke I need not doubt but many ther be that knowes and remembers the laſt mortality of this land, when in one yeere there died, one hundred and odde thouſands in <hi>London.</hi> And as concerning what hath happened by fire, Saint <hi>Edmundsbury,</hi> and <hi>Tiberton</hi> in Deuonſhire, and many other places in <hi>England,</hi> to their great griefes too truely can teſtifie, and what greeuous deluges. what outragious inundations, what vnreſiſtable ouerflowings of mercileſſe waters we haue had, nor man, nor hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie recording the like (ſince the generall flood,) wherein many hundreds of acres of paſture and erable land, was (in little ſpace as it were) turnd into a maine Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that the fiſhes (the inhabitants of the ſea) floating in their new made regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, did feede on the drowned carka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of men, women, children, and beaſts.
<pb facs="tcp:20796:5"/> What ſterility and baineneſſe of our fruitfull mother earth wee haue had, through the anger of God, withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the raine, and ſhutting the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Heauen, (that the ſenceleſſe ground hath gaped to Heauen for reliefe, when wee our ſelues haue ſcarce opened our mouthes to deſire Gods fauour) it is ſufficiently knowne to all eſtates &amp; ages. What hurts, damages, and irrecouerable loſſes and hinderances men haue ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by tempeſtuous winds, both on land and ſea, where on the land, ſteeples, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, chimneyes, trees, and diuers other things that were for the neceſſarie vſe of all ſorts of people, hath beene vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſubuerted and throwne downe, to the vtter vndoing of ſome, and to the great impoueriſhing of manie. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides to leaue the land, and to recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat what great &amp; manifold harmes hath bin vpon the ſea, the outragious windes making it altogether vnnauigable.
<pb facs="tcp:20796:6"/> Of the which to write in euery particular were a world of worke: but all theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid grieuous calamities, we muſt all confeſſe and acknowledge, to be the true tokens that our mercifull God is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended with vs; and almoſt the third part of the people in this kingdome, doe and wil euer remember ſome one or other of theſe precedent afflictions, ſome by loſſe of friends by death, and ſome by loſſe of goods, by fier, water, or other meanes; ſo that there is not, nor hath not beene, (nor I doubt will not be) any day, night, houre, or minute, wherein God hath not, doth not, or wil not powre down his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance by one meanes or other, in one place or another vpon impenetrable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repenting perfidious people.</p>
            <p>But leauing this perambulation or te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious trauell to demonſtrate that which hath been before diuulged to the publike view of the world, I doe now intend to ſhew thee, good Reader (if thou beeſt ſo)
<pb facs="tcp:20796:6"/> what incomparable harmes, and neuer to be regained loſſe hath happened by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of theſe late tempeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s windes: and though I haue not knowledge of al the hurts that are done, yet I know too much, and I with with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my heart, that this which I meane to write were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but fiction, but yet aſſure thy ſelfe thou hadſt better beleeue me then to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell to diſproue me (as the prouerbe ſaies) for I my ſelfe am ſure that the moſt part of what I write is true on mine owne knowledge, and the reſt I haue gathered by relation from many husbandies wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, fatherleſſe ſonnes, and ſoules fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers, maſterleſſe ſeruants, and maſters that haue loſt their ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts from many good and ſubſtantiall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, whoſe lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table loſſes haue too too much impoueriſht their former e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, the vnconſcionable al-deuowring Sea, being needleſly made rich, with their ſometimes hopeful adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures. But to the purpoſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:7"/>
            <p>Some certain daies before Chriſtmas (by the outragious bluſtering tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wind and weather) a very faire and tall ſhip, called the Mary of <hi>Albrogh,</hi> comming from <hi>Burdeux</hi> with one hundred and twenty tunnes of French wine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maſter <hi>Edmunds</hi> being maſter of her, was by force of weather driuen vpon the coaſt of <hi>France,</hi> neere a place called Saint <hi>Iohns,</hi> not farre from the famous and ancient City of <hi>Bullen,</hi> moſt miſerably caſt away, where was a great loſſe of ſhip &amp; goods: but God bee praiſed all the men were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued except one.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time there came a ſhip of <hi>Dartmouth</hi> from <hi>Marſeles,</hi> laden with oyles, and cotten wools, which was vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame coaſt, and neere the ſame place caſt away, where the ſhip was torn in peeces, &amp; the goods ſunke in the ſeas: but God in his mercy ſaued all the men, to doe their countrey more fortunate ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice hereafter (I hope.)</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:7"/>
            <p>Another (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>) being called the Patience, who had been heere once this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ter from <hi>Burde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x,</hi> and was bound thither againe, was caſt away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſunk in the riuer of <hi>Thames</hi> a little below <hi>Graueſend,</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a place called <hi>Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie Naſſe,</hi> the maſters name of hir was <hi>Iohn Loue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another great ſhip of <hi>London</hi> called the <hi>Hermit,</hi> of the burden of ſeuenſcore tuns or thereabouts, being bownd from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> into <hi>Cornwall</hi> for ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the owner of her being in her, whoſe name was maſter <hi>Goodlad,</hi> a man ſufficiently knowne for his credit and ſufficiencie in Nauigation, and one Maſter <hi>Wolfe</hi> being with him as maſter of the ſaid ſhip, hauing certain paſſengers abord with them; they were all moſt miſerably drowned in the briniſh waues of the merciles ſea, and the ſhip beaten in peeces againſt the hard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morceles rockes, where the wind &amp; ſeas did driue the liueles corſes vpon the ſands
<pb facs="tcp:20796:8"/> where as it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, was a woman, who with a young childe of hers was drowned in the company, who was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp on the ſhore with her childe in her armes: for being the naturall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mother of it, the ſhewed being dead (in ſpight of death) a good pattern of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate and motherly loue.</p>
            <p>A ſhippe belonging to a towne in <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall</hi> called <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o,</hi> of the burden of threeſcore run, laden with ſalt fiſh, was caſt away and ſhake in the Weſt part of <hi>England</hi> at a place called <hi>Scilla,</hi> or neere thereabouts, on the 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. of December laſt, 1612.</p>
            <p>A little Barke of <hi>Fawmouth</hi> of ſome fiue and thirty tun, was beaten on the <hi>Ile of Wight</hi> and caſt away, the ſame day afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide.</p>
            <p>And it is reported for certainty, that vpon all the ſhores and ſea ſands along the coaſt of <hi>Pickardy</hi> in <hi>France</hi> neere <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> and ſo along towardes the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide (place of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi>) doe floate
<pb facs="tcp:20796:8"/> and he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of drowne carkaſes, ſome ſay more, and ſome leſſe, but it is crediblie in formed that eleuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> twelue hundred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the leaſt.</p>
            <p>Moreouer the tide b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate belonging to <hi>Greene Hith</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> was by force of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſunk, and three paſſengers drownd, and much goodes loſt on the 30. of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember laſt.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake of the harmes in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar that is done amongſt poore water mens boates and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (betweene <hi>Graue ſend</hi> and <hi>Windſor</hi>) were a tedious peece of work, but this I know, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are much hindered by the loſſe and ſplitting of their boates and all of them generally haue had a worſer time of it then the great froſt.</p>
            <p>I omit to ſpeak in particular of diuers perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; that are reported to lie ſcattered &amp; drawned on the coaſts of this kingdome in diuers and ſundry places, &amp; all alongſt
<pb facs="tcp:20796:9"/> the coaſts of <hi>France</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, with <hi>Ireland, Scotland,</hi> and the Iles adiacent: all which as ſoone as I can get true information of, I will cauſe to bee publiſhed. Beſides I ſpeake not of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable damages, by the ſinking of certaine cole-ſhips, being bound from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> al which I wil here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after diuulge. And now leauing the ſea, let vs treat a little of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d harmes that are done now of late by theſe great windes.</p>
            <p>At the old ſwan in <hi>Thames</hi> ſtreete neere <hi>London</hi> Bridge on Chriſtmas euen was the houſe of one Maſter <hi>Pyts</hi> a ſilke dier, violently blowne downe, and in the fall did breake the roofe and tiles of another houſe that was ouer againſt it, and in the ſame pariſh in Katherine wheele al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley was a chimney blowne downe of one Maſter <hi>Baits,</hi> which brake down the cop of one <hi>Henry Goſſons</hi> houſe a Stationer, and it fell with ſuch a violence in the
<pb facs="tcp:20796:9"/> night, that it beat through the roofe and a garret, and into a middle chamber: but God be praiſed it hurt no body.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Byſhopſgate</hi> ſtreete ouer againſt the Kings head, neere the gate, was the top of a bakers houſe blowne downe, his wife and he being in bed, and the maine beame of the houſe brake, and fell downe on the teſtor of their bed, and it did no more hurt, but ſcar them: beſides chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, houſes, windmils, and diuers other buildings, ſome blowne downe, ſome much defaced, which wil not be repaired without exceſſiue charges.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon of the great ſtore of raine, which hath falne the high-waies are ſo ouerflowne, that in many places both horſe and men haue beene forced to ſwimme in the very rode way, by which meanes the City of <hi>London</hi> cannot be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with ſuch prouiſion of victuals as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers people were wont to bring in out of the countrey.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:10"/>
            <p>Then let vs conſider with our ſelues, in what dangerous eſtates wee are in when the Almighty is offended with vs, and let vs turn to the Lord through har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty repentance, and earneſt deſire of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, and then (no doubt but God in his mercy will turne his fauourable countenance towards vs. For it is neuer too late to amend, and therefore in the feare of the Lord, let euerie one mend one: and that the fame may be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, I hartely deſire of God for Chriſts ſake to giue all true Chriſtians vpright and new hearts, for Newyeeres gifts.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:20796:10"/>
            <head>THeſe things heereafter following were rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to me by Certaine Saylers and Countrey people, ſince the firſt were printed: and as for the truth of them I beleeue them my ſelfe, but I haue no authority to inforce other mens faiths, and therefore I leaue them to cenſure as they pleaſe.</head>
            <p>AS two men were Riding out in the North Contry together (being both brothers, which I know and can produce if need require) by a violent blaſt of winde they were ouerthrowne, and after they were riſen againe, (for the ſpace of an houre) one of them was ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken blinde, but afterward his ſight came to him againe.</p>
            <p>At a place cald <hi>Layton</hi> in Kent (two or three miles from <hi>Greenewich</hi>) by a furious tempeſtuous ſtorme of winde and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:20796:11"/> a faire houſe of one Maiſter <hi>Winters</hi> was blowne downe, and in the fall, a youth of the age of 15. yeares was cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other fearefull and terrible iudgements God hath powred downe vpon vs, as Rods and ſcourges for our obſtinate, wilfull, and rebellious liuing: for we (like Oxen or brute beaſts, fat our ſelues in ſinne againſt the day of ſlaughter:) &amp; (like fooliſh ſchoole-boyes) neuer feare the Rod before wee feele it: let vs then conſider our owne miſerable eſtates how we are altogether wicked, and therfore iuſtly puniſhed by that God who is altogether good, how though our faultes be as countles as the ſands of the ſea, or the Starres of Heauen, yet God hath as many ſeuerall ſortes of plagues as man hath Crimes to deſerue them: but the Lord in the midſt of his iudgements remembers mercy, or elſe we ſhould all be confounded in his heauy
<pb facs="tcp:20796:11"/> diſpleaſure: and therefore let vs thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully prayſe God for his mercy, that we are not caſt headlong to the pitte of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Perdition, according to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts and merits. From the which, the Lord God of his exceeding and ſuper-abounding mercy, for his deerely beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake to deliuer vs. To whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct perſons, and one Eternall, inuiſible, infinite, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall God, be duely rendred (of men and Angels) all Honor, Glory, praiſe, power, maieſty, might, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, now and for euermore Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
